[Music]
I could welcome all we are at the June
5th meeting of the freedom hub working
group gonna be a pretty interesting day
today again and I want to welcome our
guests as well as everyone visiting
today we're still waiting for some
people to arrive and for the one of the
couple of guests would be able to get
online here so we'll start without them
a little bit while we're feeling a
little time I just want to show you real
quick that this is the link you would
use to share this webinar series with
others and also if they just register
let's say they can't make this timeslot
with regularity because they always have
something going on just by registering
they're gonna get a reminder every week
of what's coming up for the forthcoming
Wednesday as well as a link to the last
Monday and also then there's the link
for our channel so we've got a couple
places but we're trying to help promote
brighty on a little bit frankly so we
have a channel up on that site as you
can see it up in the URL again and all
of the videos from the various webinars
we've done are in here so far and you
get a chance to review some of these too
there's been some really fantastic ones
though for those that couldn't catch
them at the time and will periodically
review them in the list of videos that
want to give up that Monday blast will
say here's some greatest hits give you a
chance to take a look at some of those
old ones Charles are you there okay no
problem
well we're waiting to get a couple of
guests on like I said so we can sort of
get a few things underway here now we're
gonna start today with John and let me
bring up his little bio here and then
we're gonna let him talk for a little
spit and then we'll bring some of the
guests and here's this government
accountability project and this was part
of the there's whistleblower activity
and so on and it's been pretty
interesting to see you know what happens
to people that are trying to do the
right thing and and he's gonna be a good
representative of that just won some
different awards and so on here I'm not
looking to take the time to go through
this whole bio here as I
got it up on the screen but John you
might want to give us a little rundown
on yourself initially and then we'll
start to go from there and I'm gonna
give you the camera here to at this
point also so here we go
so this way you can't put some stuff on
your screen if you'd like as well okay
thanks
all right and you just accept it and off
you go
all right so we're looking at your
desktop is the image part so go right
ahead please give us a little bit of a
bio and let you'd like to provide and
then let's see what you've got to lay on
us today you bet
well first of all thanks for having me
it's it's a pleasure I enjoy these
events and I'm very happy to to do one
myself so my name is John Kiriakou I am
a former CIA counterterrorism officer
and former chief investigator on the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee I
spent 15 years at the CIA the first half
of my career was in analysis the second
half was in counterterrorism operations
that's a long story that I'm gonna make
very short I switched from analysis to
counterterrorism in 1997 because I was
bored writing papers that I knew nobody
would would ever read and I wanted to do
something exciting I'm a linguist I
spoke both Arabic and Greek and I wanted
to do something that that I felt was
more of a serious contribution to the
national security and so just as I felt
like I knew what I was doing in
counterterrorism 9/11 hit and I was
named chief of counterterrorism
operations for the CIA in Pakistan so I
went to Islamabad to to take up that
position which I was thrilled to do I'd
been there for several months when we
began the hunt for Abu Zubaydah who we
believed at the time was the number
three in al-qaeda that turned out to not
exactly be correct he was certainly a
bad man he was a facilitator and a
logistician for al-qaeda
had created and managed al-qaeda's two
training camps in southern Afghanistan
he had founded al-qaeda's safehouse in
Peshawar Pakistan called the house of
martyrs so he was a bad guy it took us
about six weeks and we finally tracked
him down and on the night of March 22nd
2002 we effected 14 simultaneous raids
on 14 separate al-qaeda safe houses and
sure enough he was in one of them and we
captured him he was shot while while
trying to escape I know that sounds very
very nazi-like but Pakistani policemen
shot him as he was jumping from the roof
of his house to the roof of the
neighboring house to try to get away he
was shot in the thigh the groin and the
stomach and and was nearly killed he
nearly bled to death that very night we
rushed him first to a hospital in
Faisalabad Pakistan and then airlifted
him to a Pakistani military base nearby
outside the city of Lahore I sat with
him in that hospital room for 56
consecutive hours I never left his side
those were my orders my orders were to
fold one to take him alive which we did
barely and the other was to sit with him
and not leave his side
George tenets exact words were 24/7 CIA
eyes on and so I was frankly afraid that
I would fall asleep and that he would
escape or somebody would help him escape
or something so I tore up a sheet and I
tied him to the bed arms and legs arms
back here tied to the bedpost and the
same with his legs after about 24 hours
he came to and I'm telling you this
because it's important background when
we get into my own situation he came to
and the first thing he asked me was to
kill him he asked if I would smother him
with the pillow he was crying and he
actually cried a lot
in the period that I was with him but he
said please brother kill me take the
pillow and kill me and I said no
nobody's gonna kill you Abu Zubaydah
we've been looking for you for a very
long time and so he was very worried
about what was gonna happen to him he
asked me repeatedly what was gonna
happen and I said I frankly don't know
but I'll tell you one thing I am the
nicest guy that you are going to
encounter in this experience I said my
colleagues are not as nice as I am so if
there's one thing that you do it's that
you have to cooperate and he said you
seem like a nice man but you're the
enemy and I'll never cooperate I said
suit yourself for the next 24 hours we
talked a lot and again he cried a lot he
said he would never know the touch of a
woman he would never know the joy of
fatherhood he would never see his mother
again and I said you're not the victim
here there were 50,000 people in those
towers what did you think was gonna
happen did you think we wouldn't try to
find you to kill you lock you up to kill
bin Laden and he said that he didn't
want to attack the United States on 9/11
he wanted to attack Israel he said all
he ever wanted to do was to kill Jews
but he had been overruled that bin Laden
had made up his mind that it was going
to be the United States on 9/11 with the
idea that he wanted to crash our economy
that was what bin Laden had told him in
the middle of the night on that third
night an unmarked CIA private jet flew
in and landed he asked me to hold his
hand so I did and three FBI agents and I
carried him out on a gurney to this
airplane we maneuvered him onto the
plane and we laid him across the luggage
rack at the back I tied him down to the
luggage rack and I leaned over and I
said remember you have to cooperate and
he squeezed my hand the plane took off
I never saw him again so a couple of
months later I returned to CIA
headquarters and I had been home two or
three days I was in the cafeteria at
lunchtime and a senior officer from the
CIA's Counterterrorism Center approached
me and said very casually he said oh hey
I'm glad I ran into you I wanted to ask
you do you want to be certified in the
use of enhanced interrogation techniques
I had never heard that term before so
this was this was May late May early
June of 2002 I said what's that mean
enhanced interrogation techniques and
excitedly he said we're gonna start to
get rough with these guys and I said ooh
what's that mean and so he explained
these ten techniques to me I said I
don't know man that sounds like a
torture program torture is illegal and
he said no no it's not torture program
we got it approved by the Justice
Department and the White House I said be
that as it may I'm one of those rare
people who's actually read the United
Nations Convention Against Torture
and that's a torture program but I said
you know what let me think about it for
an hour so I went upstairs to the to the
seventh floor of the CIA that's the
executive level there was a very senior
CIA officer up there for whom I had
worked in the Middle East about a decade
earlier and I knocked on his door and I
said I said I need some advice
they just approached me and asked me if
I wanted to be certified in these
enhanced interrogation techniques what
do you think of this and he said first
of all let's call a spade a spade he
said it's a torture program they can use
whatever euphemism they want but this is
a torture program and torture is a
slippery slope and you know how these
guys are somebody's going to go
overboard in an interrogation and
they're gonna kill a prisoner and when
that happens there's going to be a
congressional investigation and there's
going to be a Justice Department
investigation and somebody's going to be
arrested and jailed he said do you want
to go to jail I said no I don't want to
go to jail
it turned out I was the only person who
went to jail but I said no I don't want
to go to jail I went back down to the
counterterrorism center I said this is a
torture program I am NOT interested
count me out now ironically motion panel
met just a couple of days later now here
I've just caught the number three in
al-qaeda and I was passed over for
promotion
you
friends of mine are our children played
together we we would go to dinner
together our wives were friends I like
these guys they were friends and I
realized then that that they had a dark
side that I just had never really
recognized I guess is the word
so I declined I was not interested in
this torture program and I went on to to
be the executive assistant to the deputy
director I had a great career early 2004
I resigned and I went into the private
sector
fast forward to December in 2007 I've
been out of the CIA almost four years at
this point and I get a call from Brian
Ross at ABC News the Brian's a famous
newsman 14 time Emmy winner one of the
longest-serving investigative
journalists out there I didn't know
Brian but he called me and he said that
he had a source who told him that I had
tortured Abu Zubaydah I said that was
absolutely untrue
I had never laid a hand on Abu Zubaydah
or any other prisoner I said indeed I
was the only person who was kind to Abu
Zubaydah the only one I said your source
is either misinformed or he's a liar and
Brian responded and I had no idea that
this was an old reporter's trick but he
said well you're welcome to come on the
show and defend yourself I said I'll
think about it later in the week
President Bush gave a press conference
and during the course of that press
conference he looked directly into the
camera and he said we do not torture I
said to my wife who was a senior CIA
officer as well I said he is a
bald-faced liar he is looking the
American people in the eye and he's
lying to us but still I kept my mouth
shut
and then a couple of days after that the
president's on his way to the helicopter
on the South Lawn of the White House and
a reporter shouts a question to him and
he turns and says well if there is
torture it's the result of a rogue CIA
officer and I said to my wife
Brian Ross's sources at the White House
and they're gonna pin this on me
and I decided that I could no longer
wait for somebody who was actually
involved in the torture program by
torturing somebody to come forward and
go public with his information I decided
I would do it and I decided in the days
leading up to that interview with Brian
Ross that no matter what he asked me I
would just tell the truth
a week later I gave him that interview
here in Washington and I said three
things three things that have utterly
changed the course of the rest of my
life I said that the CIA was torturing
its prisoners I said that torture was
official US government policy it was not
the result of a rogue as the president
had intimated and I said that the policy
had been personally approved by the
President himself as you can imagine the
FBI began investigating me the very next
day the CIA filed what's called a crimes
report indicating that I had revealed
classified information and from December
of 2007 to December of 2008 the FBI
investigated me they determined in
December of 2008 that I had not
committed a crime and they closed the
case they sent my lawyers something
called a declination letter declining to
prosecute me my wife and I actually went
out to dinner that night we were so
happy we said well this is the end of
our year-long nightmare three weeks
later Barack Obama becomes president and
he names John Brennan the deputy
national security adviser John John is
an old nemesis of mine I I met John in
1989 and we didn't like each other then
and we've never liked each other since
what I did not know was that
Obama became president John Brennan
asked the Justice Department to secretly
reopen the case against me I had no idea
that for the next three years until
January of 2012 that Robert Muller had
created something called the John
Kiriakou
task force at the FBI there were a dozen
FBI agents on me 24/7
they were intercepting my phone calls
they were intercepting my emails I had
no idea finally in January of 2012 I was
arrested and charged with five felonies
including three counts of espionage
coming out of that ABC News interview
now espionage is one of the gravest
crimes with which an American can be
charged and it frequently carries with
it the death penalty the death penalty
but they were gonna go easy on me and so
on the day of my arrest they offered me
a deal plead guilty to one count of
espionage and do 45 years and one of the
FBI agents a woman said to me take the
deal mr. Kuryakin and you might live to
meet your grandchildren I said I am NOT
doing 45 minutes I haven't done anything
wrong
the laws on my side and I said to her
that day I said on the day that I took
my oath of office on my first day at the
CIA I put my right hand in the air and I
swore to uphold and to protect the
Constitution of the United States
against all enemies foreign and domestic
and I said I will not allow myself to
believe that I was the only person in
the room that day who actually meant it
I said I'm not taking your deal look the
next week they came back and they
offered me ten years take a guilty plea
to an espionage charge do ten years I
said forget it
that was a Monday on Wednesday they came
down to 8:00 and on Friday they came
down to five I had 11 lawyers the
Washington Post called my attorneys
legal
Titans the most important criminal
defense attorneys in Washington they
have represented the likes of John
Mitchell during Watergate and Monica
Lewinsky and Aldrich Ames and every big
name in Washington these guys have
represented one of them said to me I've
been an attorney for 50 years in this
city and I haven't never seen them come
down in time with each offer usually
when they offer you 10 years and you say
no they come back the next week and they
offer you 15 years and then 20 years but
with me they kept coming down I said why
are they doing that and he said because
they have a [__] case and they know it's
[__] so he said we're going to trial you
haven't done anything wrong
that was January of 2012 what I didn't
know was that the Justice Department
uses two techniques that are impossible
to defend against one is called charge
stacking charge stacking is let's say
you may have done something wrong maybe
you didn't either way instead of
charging you with a crime they'll charge
you with five ten twenty felonies they
force you to defend yourself until you
go bankrupt and then they come back and
they say okay we'll dismiss all the
charges but one if you take a plea what
are you gonna do you're bankrupt you
can't pay your attorneys and according
to Pro Publica which came out with a
report in November of 2012 the federal
government wins ninety eight point two
percent of their cases so do you roll
those dice knowing that you have a 1.8
percent chance of winning I said to my
lawyers I said if I end up going to
trial and I'm convicted realistically
what am I looking at here and they said
18 to 24 years well that's pretty much a
death sentence - well I figured I had
nothing to lose so we continue to go
forward in our defense
I actually hired OJ Simpson's jury
consultant if you can imagine he
happened to be the uncle of my best
friend's wife and so he did it for for
nothing and we got him a security
clearance he went through all of the
files and we all sat down all 11 lawyers
with him and me and he said listen the
other technique that the Justice
Department uses is what's gonna do you
in
it's called venue shopping what they
what the prosecution does is they will
charge you with a crime in the federal
district where they are most likely to
get a conviction so let's say you run
into trouble in New York they don't
charge you in New York
they'll charge you in Washington or
Alexandria Virginia or Atlanta right
wherever they think you're gonna get a
guilty guilty decision and the longest
possible sentence that's where they
charge you well they charged me in the
Eastern District of Virginia it's known
as the espionage Court because no
national security defendant has ever won
a case their ever so I knew what my
chances were my chances were nil there's
also one judge judge Leonie brinkema who
reserves all national security cases for
herself me Jeffrey sterling Julian
Assange Ed Snowden Zacharias Moussaoui
John Walker Lindh all of these cases
were argued before Judge Leonid brinkema
I knew I was in trouble from the
beginning because we found
exculpatory evidence in discovery of
course literally every page of my
discovery was classified we receive
15,000 pages of discovery among the
discovery we found several things that I
thought pushed us over the finish line
one was a series of memos between John
Brennan and Eric Holder John Brennan
sent a memo to Eric Holder and he said
charged him with espionage and Holder
wrote back and said my people don't
think he committed espionage and Brennan
wrote back and said charge him anyway
and make him defend himself that was one
thing the other thing was when I was
working for the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee between 2009 and 2011 I was
John Kerry's intelligence advisor in
addition to being the senior
investigator on the committee one of the
wonderful things about a job on the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee is
that you get to have lunch with foreign
diplomats all the time and you can talk
about all the issues of the day and
foreign affairs that was my life and so
I loved doing that one day I got a call
from a Japanese diplomat who invited me
to lunch we go to lunch and I remember
the lunch being delightful we talked
about Israeli elections Turkish
elections the peace process terrific
lunch at the end of the lunch this guy
says to me so what's next for you and
then said well actually I think I'm
gonna resign soon I promise Senator
Kerry I'd give them two years it's been
two and a half I have five kids I need
to make some money and get my kids
through college very excitedly this guy
says no don't do that if you give me
information I can give you money and I
said to him what's the matter with you
you know how many times in my career
I've made that pitch shame on you
cold pitching me like that what's the
matter with you and I excused myself and
I walked directly to the office of the
Senate security officer without stopping
directly I went in and I said I was just
pitched by
foreign intelligence officer he asked me
what the story was I told him what had
happened at the lunch he said all right
write it up as a memo I'm gonna send it
to the FBI he did that so two days later
two FBI agents come to see me and they
said okay here's what we want you to do
we want you to call him back invite him
to lunch and try to get him to tell you
exactly what information he wants and
how much he's willing to pay for it I
said okay I'm a patriot
you want me to wear a wire or something
they said no we'll just be at the next
table we'll listen the whole
conversation I said terrific the next
week they called me the day of the lunch
and they said that something had come up
they couldn't be there but go ahead and
do the lunch write up another memo and
send it to them so I did and then they
asked me to do it a second time and a
third time and a fourth time which I did
and after each lunch I would write the
memo and I would send it to the FBI we
learned in discovery that there was no
Japanese diplomat he was an FBI agent
undercover trying to get me to commit
real espionage trying to get me to take
money in exchange for classified
information but I kept reporting the
meetings back to the FBI and finally
Peter Strock who later became infamous
on his own said look he's not going to
take the bait we might as well just end
this operation and they did so we wanted
to declassify all of this evidence of
entrapment in addition to declassifying
the fact that I was not guilty on the
facts I was not guilty of the crime for
which I was charged that there was a
disgruntled CIA officer named Steven Kim
in Bethesda Maryland who had leaked this
information as classified information
for which I was charged judge brinkema
set aside two days for us to argue our
motions we we filed 70 separate motions
to declassify 70 separate documents
crucial to my defense on the day of the
hearing we went in and judge brinkema
said I'm gonna make this easy for
everybody I have decided to deny all 70
of these motions and my lawyers objected
she overruled them my lawyers called for
something called I forget what it was
called but what it was effectively was
an in-camera interview with the judge
she denied that but she did agree to an
in-camera interview with the prosecutors
when she came out of that meeting she
reiterated her denial of our objection
as we were walking out of the court I
said to my lead attorney what just
happened in there and he said we just
lost the case that's what happened he
said we can't defend you she won't allow
us to defend you we can't use any of
that exculpatory evidence because it's
classified I said well now what do we do
he said now we talked about a plea well
the FBI knew that they they had me
because I I was simply unable to defend
myself and they came back and they said
five years I said forget it I'll go to
trial they said you'll lose at trial I
said I don't care because if I go to
trial I'm going to testify on my own
behalf and I might accidentally talk
about some of the hideous crimes against
humanity and war crimes that I've
witnessed with my own eyes in 15 years
at the CIA and so they came back and
they said all right two and a half years
you do 23 months take it or leave it
you have until nine o'clock tomorrow
morning my wife and I stayed up
literally all night that night and we
decided
to turn it down I was confident that I
had done nothing wrong and I convinced
myself that once I got in front of a
jury they would realize how ridiculous
this was what a miscarriage of justice
this was so I called my attorneys at 7
a.m. and I said I decided to turn down
the deal I'm going to trial two of the
attorneys drove to my house and the one
that I liked and respected the most
pulled me aside and angrily said you
know what your problem is your problem
is you think this is about justice it's
not about justice it's about mitigating
damage take the deal if you were my
brother I would beg you to take the deal
and I realized then at that moment the
internet I never had a chance from the
beginning the deck was stacked when you
have the FBI the CIA and the Justice
Department stacked up against you with
an unlimited budget literally an
unlimited budget and they've already
spent six million dollars of the
taxpayers money to send you to a
low-security prison for twenty three
months you can't win well that's what
this jury consultant told me if we were
in any other district in America he said
I would tell you let's go for it we're
gonna win this thing
but the Eastern District of Virginia you
don't have a prayer and so I took the
deal now more information has come out
in the interim actually since I got home
from prison in February of 2015
two of those 12 FBI agents have actually
called me to apologize and say that this
was a political case they were sorry but
they were forced to do it
we've learned that this was completely
and totally at the instigation of John
Brennan because he was living that I had
exposed the CIA's dirty laundry in
public and I had confirmed that the CIA
was indeed
during its prisoners remember John
Brennan was the executive director of
the CIA at the time he was the number
three ranking officer at the CIA and he
was in up to his neck in the george w
bush torture program which barack obama
helped to cover up so i learned a lot
one of the things that i learned is that
i'm a whistleblower you know the the day
after my arrest I sought out jesselyn
Radack at the Government Accountability
Project
jesselyn Radack specializes in the
defense of whistleblowers and I I said
listen I've got to thank you for taking
my case I know that you only take the
cases of whistleblowers and I'm not a
whistleblower and she chuckled and she
said you're the poster boy of
whistleblowing and I said no I'm not I'm
just I'm just a guy who saw an
illegality and said something and she
said look there's actually a legal
definition of whistleblowing it's
bringing to light any evidence of waste
fraud abuse illegality or threats to the
public health or public safety that's
exactly what you did and she said that
in her experience with the exception at
the time of Daniel Ellsberg and since
then also of Ed Snowden that no whistle
blower thinks he's a whistleblower they
have to be told that they're
whistleblowers I've been asked a
thousand times why I did what I did and
I've repeated the same answer a thousand
times and that is that I have always
been a firm and staunch believer in the
Constitution and in the rule of law
that's what separates us from every
other country either we're that shining
city on a hill that Ronald Reagan talked
about or we're not either we're a beacon
of hope for human rights and civil
rights and civil liberties or were not
you know
I spent three years on assignment at the
State Department at the American Embassy
in Manama Bahrain and in that job I was
the human rights officer which meant
that I had to write the Human Rights
report every year it's an annual report
mandated by Congress now imagine going
into the Minister of interiors office
and saying your excellency you cannot
scoop up a fifteen year old kid in front
of his school beat him to death and then
dump his body in front of his parents
house you cannot kill people extra
judicially I have to write that in the
human rights report that is a violation
of international law and then 15 minutes
later the CIA go officer goes in to meet
the same Minister of Interior and says
don't listen to the State Department guy
we'll cover for you we want you to open
a secret prison where we can bring these
people that we kidnap overseas that
nobody knows about
and then you torture them for us and
then you give us transcripts of
everything they say what do you think
they're gonna do you think they're gonna
listen to the State Department human
rights guy or you think they're gonna
cash the CIA's check and do what the CIA
station chief tells them to do we can't
be both of those countries either we're
a nation governed by a living and
breathing Constitution or we're not and
I have always believed that we were and
that's worth fighting for and so you
know prison was hard hard hard I
actually wrote a book about it called
doing time like a spy how the CIA taught
me to survive and thrive in prison it
won two literary awards if you can even
believe that but I was serious in my
convictions in my beliefs that we're the
good guys and if we are going to be the
good guys we have to select the good
guys
the rest of the world looks to us for
leadership and so we have to lead even
if that leadership is sometimes
domestically painful and so with that we
have 19 minutes I'm happy to take any
any calls or
comments that questions that anybody may
have well that was pretty amazing I
would have to say and it was curious
they didn't know the actual outcome the
world what did have materially had to
take the deal in the end though just
goes to show like so they had a pretty
weak case if they kept wit whittling it
down and wheeling it down just to get
you to say yes to something yes before I
kind of open up I didn't want to get a
couple comments that we came because
Heidi was able to have meanders to get
online here Heidi are you there hello
yes thank you welcome wanted to kind of
get some comment area and what he had to
say and a little bit about kind of your
experiences too and probably give it a
little fast bio on yourself if you would
great um John wow that's really really
quite a story I'm proud to call you a
brother-in-arms psycho baby
um a little bio about myself you want me
to start in ah yes
jump right in there with both feet okay
great
my name is Heidi Weber I am a higher
education whistleblower in the college
or university realm I was a Dean at a
for-profit college in based out of the
Minnesota Wisconsin area and the school
had approximately 25 different campuses
under different names and such
throughout the United States so although
the majority of them are in the Midwest
here I grew up in South Dakota my dad
was a deputy sheriff when I was younger
and taught me a lot about ethics I mean
that he was a very very big proponent of
ethics doing the right thing
volunteering for your country and and
being a patriot so he instilled all
those things in me and my mom too you
know she she was right behind him
teaching those things as well and so I
grew up with that in the back of my mind
I started working for this university
system which
to be a for-profit college university
system and that it's different than a
state school or even a private college
system where they've been around for you
know hundreds of years and have a
foundation and all those sorts of things
in place for-profit colleges kind of
popped up from the 80s until now their
primary goal is you know to be run as a
business and you know a lot of them do
it a great way they really do a lot of a
lot of those for-profit schools are good
they give people a good education
started seeing all these things going on
at the school I was at I was promoted
quickly I was named faculty member of
the year a year after I started promoted
moved to the Twin Cities area from South
Dakota and I I really started seeing a
pattern at that point you know before I
had just been at a single campus
watching all these things go on and and
then when I got up here as Dean in
corporate I started seeing a pattern at
every campus well long story short my
dad had kidney cancer and he ended up
passing away about a year into my being
Dean at this college and the school made
me leave my dad's funeral and go to an
accreditation conference and I remember
thinking how's the longest day of my
life and I had a turning point became a
whistleblower
four years later went to trial a jury
trial and the verdict was in my favor
since then I've done a lot of other
things with whistleblowing and become an
advocate for especially women
whistleblowers there aren't that many of
us and for others as far as advocacy
because as John knows it's rough being a
whistleblower the things that you face
the scrutiny is unbelievable so that's
kind of everything in a nutshell I can
get into more detail later but that's
basically where I'm at right now I'm
starting a podcast and we're gonna dive
into a lot of different store
and really the the meat and potatoes of
what it means to be a whistleblower and
go through all of that so that's where
I'm at
do you want me to keep talking here I
can go trying to chime in for a minute
manager divvy up the time we've got so I
definitely want to kind of open up for
some questions and so yeah but the
question I would ask of both you at the
beginning because you're both coming
from completely different places as a
word even though you try to make the
same thing happen why do you assume that
so many people who's seen these sorts of
things don't become a whistleblower what
was different about the two of you was
it just because you had more ethics and
everybody else or you were less fearful
of the penalties or you were more
convinced of the fact that you were
totally right there'd be no way you'd
pay a price because you knew you were so
dead right what do you what do you what
do you think it was John do you want to
go first I'll let you go first
thank you this is a question that I've
I've asked a thousand times I've asked
experts who cover these things and there
there's an Israeli journalist who also
happens to be a psychologist by the name
of Al Press he's actually studied this
and he's written a book about it and he
said that whistleblowers have an
unusually well-defined sense of right
and wrong
far better defined than the general
public and you know at the CIA they the
culture is such that they teach us that
that everything is a shade of gray and I
came to realize that that just simply
wasn't true that some things are black
and white they're right and wrong and in
my mind this was something that was just
plain wrong the other thing for me was I
grew up in a very close-knit nuclear
family I'm the grandson of immigrants
from Greece the Greek Orthodox Church
was very important in my upbringing and
you know we talk about things like like
human rights and so I was I was raised
to to believe that on many of these
big issues these broader issues there's
a right and a wrong and people around me
at the CIA spent their time trying to
justify their actions actions that I
believed to be illegal there was no
sense in thinking about it I just knew
that it was wrong and so I think that al
presses conclusion that that
whistleblowers have this unusually
highly defined sense of right and wrong
is correct yeah I would agree I agree
with John I think you know we get into
that more in my podcasts too and about
talking that because as John said we get
that question all the time and people
asked why did you do that or they have
some they think we have some ulterior
motive or something you know
you know for money or whatever and
reality there are 2,000 whistleblower
cases filed with the government each
year and whistleblowers save American
taxpayers four billion dollars are
recovered in taxpayer money because of
whistleblowers each year and that's per
year people so it's we 2,000 cases are
filed only two or three hundred get
picked up so you have all these people
who are whistleblowers who obviously you
know did it for the right reason and not
for money because there's the odds are
against you more than they are for you
in that realm plus to just to go through
the process it's a four or five year
process to go through everything and you
have to stay strong and you have to rely
on the truth you know if you were doing
it otherwise it wouldn't work I wouldn't
imagine it has to be based on the truth
before I and I see some hands are raised
real quick before we base out on asking
this question what can any of us do to
see their help you individually or at
large and over others that are trying to
get out there's or some organizations to
get behind or I think I think well I can
speak to that first here there are a lot
of organizations but I think if they're
just the average person what I tell
people you know they look at me and say
you know you get these things called a
traitor your snitch
disloyal list or whatever you know um
and I look at him and say hey you know
when is telling the truth
rah when is that a wrong thing and then
people kind of come around and I I think
just telling people speaking up when
people use that kind of narrative or
negativity around whistleblowing and
whistleblowers will help a lot because
man you we each need that support it
helps us all and it helps every single
citizen in this country when we stand up
and if we have support that would make
it all better you know more people would
be encouraged to do it then so what
would you say Jeff I would agree with
that entirely if you're interested in
organizations certainly there's the
Government Accountability Project the
Project on Government Oversight
there's the whisper program
whistleblower and source protection
program is what it stands for you know I
just as a funny aside when I got home
from prison the Greek government hired
me to help them write a new
whistleblower protection law and so I
made ten trips to Greece over the three
years from 2015 to 2018 to meet with the
Minister of Justice and the Minister of
State for anti-corruption when I went
for the very first time
well the Minister of the Minister of
Justice asked me my Greek is very good
and so the Minister of Justice asked me
what I meant when I kept using this word
whistleblower because there's no
equivalent of it so our conversation was
in Greek except for the word
whistleblower so I explained to him in
Greek what the meaning of the word was
and he said oh you mean like a rat or a
snitch and I said no not at all like a
rat or a snitch and so we came up with
guardian of the public trust which
sounds really good in Greek but that's
what we're up against I mean this was a
friendly audience equating
whistleblowing with ratting and
snitching imagine what a hostile
audience is like and when I say hostile
audience I mean on Capitol Hill in the
oversight
mitties in the halls of the CIA and the
FBI and the Justice Department there is
a lot of work that needs to be done
absolutely that you are a hundred
percent right John you are I spoke on
Capitol Hill as well and had faced a lot
of questions from the press even you
know the media comes up with that and
I've been on CBS so and I mana CBS
Associate Producer and we are in the
second season of whistle blower right
now on CBS which paints whistle blowing
in the the light that it should be you
know we're just average people so very
nice
bright and I see ever cand up yeah the
question question for John what and what
an amazing story thank you they go my
question is what you described seems to
be sort of this this untouchability your
your experience sort of shows the
untouchability of what we call the deep
state and it really does you know to
normal people seem sort of like this
this all-powerful entity that no one
dare go up against that you really don't
have a chance against and my question is
what do you have any thoughts or any
ideas for those of us who would like to
fight that to sort of even dismantle the
deep state or you know make it such that
we're we're not up against this
all-powerful thing oh that's a great
question and it's actually a very
difficult one to answer a preface an
answer by saying that there's a there's
a Harvard Law Professor by the name of
Harvey silverglade who wrote a book in
2012 called three felonies a day and he
argues that we are so over criminalized
so over regulated in this country that
the average American on the average day
going about his or her normal business
commits three felonies with the the
lesson being if they want to get you
they're gonna get you and there's
nothing you can do to protect yourself
okay with that aside what we have to do
is to absolute ride are members of
Congress our elected official
because it's their job to provide
oversight it's their job to protect
whistleblowers and to make sure that the
American taxpayers are being well
represented and are not being robbed by
the likes of the CIA and NSA and FBI and
the rest of the deep state those
organizations have to follow the law
just like every other American does and
it's it's only Congress that can hold
them to it I'll tell you really since
9/11 the oversight committees have not
overseen anything
they've just been in chair to reader
committees and that's not what Congress
is meant to do amen to that
a Kathy I see you've got your hand up as
well Kathy are you there oh I got you
meet it for month there you go it was we
both were muted and I had you muted - by
mistake
go ahead that's okay thank you John for
your great integrity like this and I'm
just thinking considering well say Paul
Manafort has been going through it game
center Rikers Island just yesterday a
larger stone and all the people involved
in this state thing against Trump well I
mean I've heard that they've been told
that if you don't agree it isn't this
you know we want them to sing her
compose or whatever to tell a story what
kind of advice would you give people who
caught up in this kind of thing right
now
Oh be true to yourself you know one of
the things that the cost the cost of all
of this is very very high as you might
imagine I lost literally everything I
lost my pension I lost my home my wife
ran off with her boss better than being
married to me I lost everything I never
work again I mean not really
not unless some courageous you know
corporate leader decides to take a
chance on a convicted felon so the cost
is very very high but I sleep like a
baby at night because I know I did the
right thing and my kids are old enough
to articles and to watch documentaries
and my kids know I did the right thing
and so yeah you know if this is what God
intended for me that I'm just gonna have
to I'm gonna have to live with it but I
can tell you that I can sleep at night
and I don't know how some of these other
guys sleep at night yeah thank you David
I see you've got your hand there thank
you Jeff
John and Heidi this David Demarest with
roads to freedom and I've noticed that
you and Heidi share one thing and that
is you're whistleblowers against large
institutions both government and private
I'm extremely dubious about the
government policing itself on issues
like this and for that matter I'm
extremely dubious about large
institutions in general like the
education system private or public
policing themselves now I understand the
motivation the ethical motivation of
whistleblowers what do you think is the
problem with large institutions that
fosters these types of ethical problems
well thanks John I think John will
probably agree with me here and saying
that private or government they're kind
of tied together you know without
getting too political in there anything
a lot of our corporations and certain
government entities are kind of friends
with each other shall we say in
different ways and so
I think my personal opinion of why this
happens is because we have we don't have
competition anymore we don't have the
kind of competition that we need that
kind of checks and balance system that
has an equal pushback for bad behavior
you know or by a few and certainly a few
people cannot represent the entire
government or an entire corporation by
their behavior but I think we need
things in place that foster more of a
balanced system between the two so that
they are held accountable for what
they're doing and and the corporation
itself whether a government or private
can actually hold its own people more
accountable inside but that's my opinion
though I hate to sound like an echo
chamber but yeah I agree completely with
Heidi I can tell you at the CIA there is
actually one good guy and that's the
Inspector General the Inspector General
when I was there was a man by the name
of John helgerson John was already the
deputy director of the CIA when I got
hired he didn't retire until 2009 and he
was essentially forced out because he
refused to to cave in to the likes of
George tennen and John Brennan and Jose
Rodriguez and these other monsters who
created this clearly illegal program now
inspectors general do not always work
the way they're supposed to work Tom
Drake who was an NSA officer went to the
Pentagon inspector general to report on
a program where NSA was surreptitiously
spying on American citizens and the
Pentagon inspector general destroyed the
evidence that Tom brought out with him
and then tipped off the Justice
Department that Tom had reported on this
this abuse so now the DoD Inspector
General now former inspector general is
under criminal indictment for
destruction of evidence so you can't
always trust the Inspector General and
again this is why we need
well staffed and well-funded oversight
committees who have experienced
investigators on them and there are none
I mean the Intelligence Committee is
supposed to but but they're partisan and
so they don't always cooperate with one
another but this system that we that we
found ourselves in post 9/11 it's just
not workable there has to be a real
change and at the very least when it
comes to national security you have to
take the partisanship out of it that's
going to be the death of us it's true -
yes we're gonna try and squeeze one more
question before I turn it over to
Charles Jamie I see you've got your hand
up yes hi everyone
you know John I think you answered a
really big part of my question was so I
I'll obby here in DC for medical freedom
in that and we're finding that almost
every single Oversight Committee is
bought and paid for it is just a mess
everyone comes in there totally
bipartisan they breathe from their
script and they leave and it is the most
unreal a natural state and no none of
these politicians are making eye contact
with anyone and they bring their people
in and they leave they're not hearing
from any sides now not just for my side
of medical freedom we're finding that
you know there's people with
institutions with a about the technology
with 5g they're not hearing it from this
side even on that I mean so I just
wanted to ask you is there anybody on
the hill that you personally stand
behind and Heidi you as well who you
felt like you've been in contact for so
many years and who you feel comfortable
with working with you know and that's it
thank you guys
great question the answer is yes there
are two people chuck Grassley is the
champion of whistleblowers on Capitol
Hill Republican senator from Iowa and
the other is Rand Paul Republican
senator from Kentucky
I've met with both of them they are only
entirely supportive of whistleblowers
and have put their own reputations on
the line to support people like like me
or Bradley Birkenfeld or Tom Drake or
bill Binney they didn't have to do that
and certainly no no the other 536
members of Congress have ever said
anything supportive so yeah those are
the the to go to people that I've dealt
with Grassley and Rand Paul no sooner is
he drown go ahead finish your comment oh
sorry about that mine are not
necessarily with the in government you
know I talked to a lot of whistleblowers
and a lot of whistleblower attorneys
which are mainly based out of Washington
DC there are a lot of them a lot of
those firms really you know I mean it's
their job but they're really fighting
for a recognition of whistleblowers and
and their rights as well so I would say
whistleblowers of America is another and
gap as John had mentioned before the
Government Accountability Project
they're really doing a lot of lobbying
to draw attention they're great people
to talk to that are nonpartisan I don't
want to say bipartisan nonpartisan maybe
because you know there's certainly
government officials who find it in
their best interest at a certain time to
you know bring up or be a champion for
whistleblowers but then when going gets
tough maybe they're not around you know
so to speak from both parties both are
there anyway there whether friends for
sure you know and some one of the other
people on the call made a comment which
is so true that once all these checks
and balances disappear then who knows
where we're gonna go we could drift into
fascism and know these big entities like
the vet and the CIA and all the rest of
them there's no taxes paid they're doing
no financial statement there's no one
knows anything what's going on with any
of these organizations let alone the
individuals that are passing rules and
regulations that willy-nilly and
what-have-you so it is a disaster we
need to get control of Charles we're a
little past our time here you want to
kind of ask any last question of your
own and kind of give us a preview of
what's coming up the next couple we
well sir Jeff and you know we've gone to
in hours let me wrap it up quick preview
and thanks John and howdy has fantastic
I mean if we don't respect
whistleblowers how can we ever know
what's going on in the bowels of the
government so I know John you know I
spoke a a year ago so expanding
whistleblower rights to the national
security employees so if you want to say
something that a specific expansion that
still is needed oh I think I think so I
think that there ought to be one focal
point on Capitol Hill for whistleblower
liaison instead of going to the general
counsel and then the Inspector General
and through your chain of command and
then you go to the you know to the
general Oversight Committee there should
be one person an ombudsman that you can
go directly to and report waste fraud
abuse and illegality we're not there yet
and and I'll tell you things work far
better in the Senate than they do in the
house the house is just a just it's a
basket trance chaos between the
Republicans and the Democrats on the
Intelligence Committee it's unworkable
the Senate is better but we can be
better still true the House Senate
Veterans Affairs Committee is meeting on
some whistleblower things with witnesses
and a couple of weeks so I'm just
throwing that out there in case anybody
wants to help out and support them and
Heidi how can folks watch our CBS show
or your podcast you can go to once it's
live we're talking the June here right
now season two of whistleblower on CBS
is running on Friday night
it showcases one whistleblower per week
their story basically like John's story
from beginning to end my story was
featured in season one is the season
finale but the ones and two are pretty
good I've helped find a lot of them so
I've talked to a lot of whistleblowers
also my podcast is just diving deeper
into it and it's going to be
joon-hee got a whistle-blower revolution
calm fantastic and jeff real quick so
next year I mean next week we have
Leonard read the founder of the
foundation for economic education as my
son yells at me in the background and
then in two weeks hence Hawaii's think
tanker about how to open up the freight
travel lanes with the Jones Act and then
Robert pull from The Reason Foundation
on speeding up the roads and then I must
now Adam Koch cash and weather will get
bigger issues on the presidential
campaign
so with that Jeff I will meet myself
okay very good
appreciate that everyone being here
today we you know obviously we could
have kept going here this was really an
exciting episode as usual and we're
gonna want to circle back and see how
things continue to you know move forward
for all of these issues we've been
covering so I appreciate the two of you
making it here today and everybody else
and I'll see in a week and then I said
again I'm Monday I will send a notice
out so we'll have a link to the
recording of this as well as announcing
Leonard Reed and a little preview of
what he's gonna be talking about so
thanks all and pass the word around
about us and share some of those videos
on our Channel
[Music]
you